<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Internationalization</title>

  <note>
    <para>
      Some regions run Red&nbsp;Hat training in classrooms which by policy should be localized for the language in which the course is being taught.
      The classroom setup process deploys all machines and users localized for <code>en-US.utf8</code> (US English).
    </para>
    <para>
      If your classroom needs to be set to a different locale, this section must be covered.
      The instructor should guide students through appropriate language and input configuration for their locale and hardware.
      The instructor should then have students save the settings to their baseline machine images with <code>rht-vmctl</code>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Per the directions in <code>ClassroomSetup.txt</code>, the locale settings for the physical layer (<code>foundation<replaceable>X</replaceable></code>) are inherited from the manual selections made when <code>foundation0</code> was installed.
      Modifying the locale in the pre-built virtual machine images should be done as an exercise with the students updating and saving each of their virtual machines using <code>rht-vmctl save VMNAME</code> as described in the final step of the <quote>DETAILED INSTRUCTIONS</quote> in <code>ClassroomSetup.txt</code>.
    </para>
    <para>
      For other locations, this section is optional.
    </para>
  </note>

  <task role="Lecture">
    <title>Language Support</title>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          Explain to your students that Red&nbsp;Hat Enterprise&nbsp;Linux officially supports a large number of languages.
          The book references the list at the time of writing.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Official support</emphasis> means that there is a certain level of support for the language in the operating system, customers can recieve support for technical issues with those languages, and can ask for correction of internationalization/localization (i18n/l10n) issues if there are problems.
          It does not imply that communication with technical support representatives will be available in their native language.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
          It may be possible to use unsupported languages on the system, but customers might not recieve support for technical issues with those languages.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </task>

  <section>
    <title>Per-user Language Selection</title>

    <para>
      This subsection discusses GNOME 3 language settings for an individual user.
      It is divided into two chunks: how to set the language/locale correctly, and how to set the input method for the locale correctly.
    </para>

    <para>
      If your classroom machines need to have a locale and input method other than the defaults set, use this subsection as a workshop.
      Have the students follow along with you in order to set up their machines.
      At the end of the section, they will need to save their settings to their baseline machine images so that the localization persists across server resets.
    </para>

    <task role="Lecture">
      <title>Language Settings</title>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Mention that GNOME 3 may prompt a user for their preferred language on first login (through <code>/usr/libexec/gnome-initial-setup</code>).
            This may be disabled by the classroom setup process, but if it is available that is one way to set preferred locale.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            Demonstrate <code>gnome-control-center region</code>.
            For System Administration I, one way would be to use the GNOME GUI to select <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>(Username)</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> and open the <application>Region &amp; Language</application> application.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            Mention that these settings will only affect GNOME 3 sessions, not <code>ssh</code> logins or logins on a text console.
            Optionally mention the Note box with the shell snippet on how to tie together the GNOME locale for ssh and console logins in RHEL 7.
            The RHEL 6 file used by GNOME was not in <code>/var/lib</code>, but was <code>${HOME}/.dmrc</code>.
          </para>

          <important>
            <para>
              The kernel's physical console/virtual consoles (<code>$TERM="linux"</code>) barely support Western European fonts, and do not support non-Latin text well at all.
              Locales this definitely impacts: <code>ja-JP</code>, <code>ko-KR</code>, <code>zh-CN</code>, and <code>zh-TW</code>.
            </para>
            <para>
              For affected languages, the sample code either should not be used, or should check to see if $TERM="linux" and $LANG is one of the affected languages, and if so sets it to <code>en_US.UTF-8</code>.
              A good example of how to do this is in <code>/etc/profile.d/lang.sh</code>.
            </para>
          </important>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            Explain the format of the <code>LANG</code> variable: <replaceable>language</replaceable>_<replaceable>REGION</replaceable>.<replaceable>ENCODING</replaceable>.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            Explain that single commands can be run in a different language by setting the <code>LANG</code> variable just for that command.
          </para>

          <para>
            Demo the following command:
          </para>

<screen><code>LANG=ja_JP.UTF-8 ls nosuchfile</code></screen>

          <para>
            If Japanese fonts are not yet installed a dialog will pop-up to ask if you want to install them.
            Click on <guibutton>Install</guibutton> and enter the <code>root</code> password when prompted.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </task>

    <task role="Lecture">
      <title>Input Method Settings</title>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Demonstrate how to add additional input methods to the system with the <application>Region &amp; Language</application> application.
            Either add the input method appropriate to your locale, or add the <guilabel>English (international AltGr dead keys)</guilabel> method as an example.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            Explain to your students that to switch between input methods they can use <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> (also known as <keycombo><keycap>Windows</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>).
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            If your chosen input method has special features (such as the <guilabel>Japanese (Kana Kanji)</guilabel> method), demonstrate them here.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </task>

    <task role="Lecture">
      <title>System-wide Default Language Settings</title>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Discuss (and optionally demonstrate) how <code>localectl set-locale</code> can be used to set the system-wide default language.
            Mention how settings are saved in <code>/etc/locale.conf</code>.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            We do not discuss setting console keyboard settings here in depth, but if you need to do so, cover <code>localectl</code> and <code>/etc/vconsole.conf</code>.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            Optionally, you may mention that <code>/etc/profile.d/lang.sh</code> will cause the system console to use <code>en_US.UTF-8</code> instead of the configured system-wide locale for languages which are not well supported by the locale.
            (If the student sets <code>$LANG</code> manually after that startup script runs, that will not happen.)
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </task>

    <task role="Lecture">
      <title>Language Packs</title>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Explain that language packs install helper packages that include translated man pages, help pages, spelling dictionaries, and other supporting files.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            <code>yum langavailable</code> shows available packs
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            <code>yum langlist</code> shows installed packs
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            <code>yum langinstall <replaceable>code</replaceable></code> installs a language pack
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </task>
  </section>
</section>
