<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % common_entities SYSTEM "../common.ent" >
%common_entities;
]>
<section>
  <title>Internationalization</title>

  <!-- Commenting out since we can't confirm the current list.
    Need to identify where authoritative information on the supported languages is. -->

  <!--
    Red&nbsp;Hat Enterprise&nbsp;Linux officially supports 22 languages: English, Assamese, Bengali,
    Chinese (Simplified), Chinese (Traditional), French, German, Gujarati, Hindi, Italian, Japanese,
    Kannada, Korean, Malayalam, Marathi, Odia, Portuguese (Brazilian), Punjabi, Russian, Spanish,
    Tamil, and Telugu.
    -->

  <section>
    <title>Per-user Language Selection</title>

    <para>
      Your users might prefer to use a different language for their desktop environment than the system-wide default.
      They might also want to use a different keyboard layout or input method for their account.
    </para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Language Settings</title>
      <para>
        In the GNOME desktop environment, the user might be prompted to set their preferred language and input method on first login.
        If not, then the easiest way for an individual user to adjust their preferred language and input method settings is to use the <application>Region &amp; Language</application> application.
      </para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>
      You can start this application in two ways.
      You can run the command <code>gnome-control-center region</code> from a terminal window, or on the top bar, from the system menu in the right corner, select the settings button (which has a crossed screwdriver and wrench for an icon) from the bottom left of the menu.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the window that opens, select <application>Region &amp; Language</application>.
      Click the <guilabel>Language</guilabel> box and select the preferred language from the list that appears.
      This also updates the <guilabel>Formats</guilabel> setting to the default for that language.
      The next time you log in, these changes will take full effect.
    </para>

    <para>
      These settings affect the GNOME desktop environment and any applications such as <code>gnome-terminal</code> that are started inside it.
      However, by default they do not apply to that account if accessed through an <code>ssh</code> login from a remote system or a text-based login on a virtual console (such as <code>tty5</code>).
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        You can make your shell environment use the same <code>LANG</code> setting as your graphical environment, even when you log in through a text-based virtual console or over <code>ssh</code>.
        One way to do this is to place code similar to the following in your <code>~/.bashrc</code> file.
        This example code will set the language used on a text login to match the one currently set for the user's GNOME desktop environment:
      </para>
<screen>i=$(grep &#x27;Language=&#x27; /var/lib/AccountsService/users/${USER} \
  | sed &#x27;s/Language=//&#x27;)
if [ &#x22;$i&#x22; != &#x22;&#x22; ]; then
    export LANG=$i
fi</screen>
      <para>
        Japanese, Korean, Chinese, and other languages with a non-Latin character set might not display properly on text-based virtual consoles.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      Individual commands can be made to use another language by setting the <varname>LANG</varname> variable on the command line:
    </para>

<screen><prompt>[user@host ~]$ </prompt><userinput>LANG=fr_FR.utf8 date</userinput>
<code>jeu. avril 25 17:55:01 CET 2019</code></screen>

    <para>
      Subsequent commands will revert to using the system's default language for output.
      The <code>locale</code> command can be used to determine the current value of <varname>LANG</varname> and other related environment variables.
    </para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Input Method Settings</title>
      <para>
        GNOME&nbsp;3 in Red&nbsp;Hat Enterprise&nbsp;Linux&nbsp;7 or later automatically uses the <application>IBus</application> input method selection system, which makes it easy to change keyboard layouts and input methods quickly.
      </para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>
      The <application>Region &amp; Language</application> application can also be used to enable alternative input methods.
      In the <application>Region &amp; Language</application> application window, the <guilabel>Input Sources</guilabel> box shows what input methods are currently available.
      By default, <guilabel>English (US)</guilabel> may be the only available method.
      Highlight <guilabel>English (US)</guilabel> and click the <guibutton>keyboard</guibutton> icon to see the current keyboard layout.
    </para>

    <para>
      To add another input method, click the <guibutton>+</guibutton> button at the bottom left of the <guilabel>Input Sources</guilabel> window.
      An <guilabel>Add an Input Source</guilabel> window displays.
      Select your language, and then your preferred input method or keyboard layout.
    </para>

    <para>
      When more than one input method is configured, the user can switch between them quickly by typing <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> (sometimes called <keycombo><keycap>Windows</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>).
      A <firstterm>status indicator</firstterm> will also appear in the GNOME top bar, which has two functions: It indicates which input method is active, and acts as a menu that can be used to switch between input methods or select advanced features of more complex input methods.
    </para>

    <para>
      Some of the methods are marked with gear icons, which indicate that those methods have advanced configuration options and capabilities.
      For example, the Japanese <guilabel>Japanese (Kana Kanji)</guilabel> input method allows the user to pre-edit text in Latin and use <keycap>Down Arrow</keycap> and <keycap>Up Arrow</keycap> keys to select the correct characters to use.
    </para>

    <para>
      US English speakers may also find this useful.
      For example, under <guilabel>English (United States)</guilabel> is the keyboard layout <guilabel>English (international AltGr dead keys)</guilabel>, which treats <keycap>AltGr</keycap> (or the right <keycap>Alt</keycap>) on a PC 104/105-key keyboard as a &quot;secondary shift&quot; modifier key and dead key activation key for typing additional characters.
      There are also Dvorak and other alternative layouts available.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Any Unicode character can be entered in the GNOME desktop environment if you know the character's Unicode code point.
        Type <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>U</keycap> </keycombo>, followed by the code point.
        After <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>U</keycap> </keycombo> has been typed, an underlined <code>u</code> character displays, indicating that the system is waiting for Unicode code point entry.
      </para>
      <para>
        For example, the lowercase Greek letter lambda has the code point U+03BB, and can be entered by typing <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>U</keycap> </keycombo>, then <code>03BB</code>, then <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>System-wide Default Language Settings</title>

    <para>
      The system's default language is set to US English, using the UTF-8 encoding of Unicode as its character set (<code>en_US.utf8</code>), but this can be changed during or after installation.
    </para>

    <para>
      From the command line, the <code>root</code> user can change the system-wide locale settings with the <code>localectl</code> command.
      If <code>localectl</code> is run with no arguments, it displays the current system-wide locale settings.
    </para>

    <para>
      To set the system-wide default language, run the command <code>localectl set-locale LANG=<replaceable>locale</replaceable></code>, where <replaceable>locale</replaceable> is the appropriate value for the <varname>LANG</varname> environment variable from the "Language Codes Reference" table in this chapter.
      The change will take effect for users on their next login, and is stored in <code>/etc/locale.conf</code>.
    </para>

<screen><prompt>[root@host ~]# </prompt><userinput>localectl set-locale LANG=fr_FR.utf8</userinput></screen>

    <para>
      In GNOME, an administrative user can change this setting from <application>Region &amp; Language</application> by clicking the <guibutton>Login Screen</guibutton> button at the upper-right corner of the window.
      Changing the <guilabel>Language</guilabel> of the graphical login screen will also adjust the system-wide default language setting stored in the <code>/etc/locale.conf</code> configuration file.
    </para>

    <important>
      <para>
        Text-based virtual consoles such as <code>tty4</code> are more limited in the fonts they can display than terminals in a virtual console running a graphical environment, or pseudoterminals for <code>ssh</code> sessions.
        For example, Japanese, Korean, and Chinese characters may not display as expected on a text-based virtual console.
        For this reason, you should consider using English or another language with a Latin character set for the system-wide default.
      </para>
      <para>
        Likewise, text-based virtual consoles are more limited in the input methods they support, and this is managed separately from the graphical desktop environment.
        The available global input settings can be configured through <code>localectl</code> for both text-based virtual consoles and the graphical environment.
        See the <code>localectl</code>(1) and <code>vconsole.conf</code>(5) man pages for more information.
      </para>
    </important>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Language Packs</title>

    <para>
      Special RPM packages called <firstterm>langpacks</firstterm> install language packages that add support for specific languages.
      These langpacks use dependencies to automatically install additional RPM packages containing localizations, dictionaries, and translations for other software packages on your system.
    </para>

    <para>
      To list the langpacks that are installed and that may be installed, use <code>yum list langpacks-*</code>:
    </para>

<screen><prompt>[root@host ~]# </prompt><userinput>yum list langpacks-*</userinput>
Updating Subscription Management repositories.
Updating Subscription Management repositories.
Installed Packages
langpacks-en.noarch      1.0-12.el8        @AppStream
Available Packages
langpacks-af.noarch      1.0-12.el8        rhel-8-for-x86_64-appstream-rpms
langpacks-am.noarch      1.0-12.el8        rhel-8-for-x86_64-appstream-rpms
langpacks-ar.noarch      1.0-12.el8        rhel-8-for-x86_64-appstream-rpms
langpacks-as.noarch      1.0-12.el8        rhel-8-for-x86_64-appstream-rpms
langpacks-ast.noarch     1.0-12.el8        rhel-8-for-x86_64-appstream-rpms
<emphasis>...output omitted...</emphasis></screen>

    <para>
      To add language support, install the appropriate langpacks package.
      For example, the following command adds support for French:
    </para>

<screen><prompt>[root@host ~]# </prompt><userinput>yum install langpacks-fr</userinput></screen>

    <para>
      Use <code>yum repoquery --whatsupplements</code> to determine what RPM packages may be installed by a langpack:
    </para>

<screen><prompt>[root@host ~]# </prompt><userinput>yum repoquery --whatsupplements langpacks-fr</userinput>
Updating Subscription Management repositories.
Updating Subscription Management repositories.
Last metadata expiration check: 0:01:33 ago on Wed 06 Feb 2019 10:47:24 AM CST.
glibc-langpack-fr-0:2.28-18.el8.x86_64
gnome-getting-started-docs-fr-0:3.28.2-1.el8.noarch
hunspell-fr-0:6.2-1.el8.noarch
hyphen-fr-0:3.0-1.el8.noarch
libreoffice-langpack-fr-1:6.0.6.1-9.el8.x86_64
man-pages-fr-0:3.70-16.el8.noarch
mythes-fr-0:2.3-10.el8.noarch</screen>

    <important>
      <para>
        Langpacks packages use RPM <firstterm>weak dependencies</firstterm> in order to install supplementary packages only when the core package that needs it is also installed.
      </para>
      <para>
        For example, when installing <package>langpacks-fr</package> as shown in the preceding examples, the <package>mythes-fr</package> package will only be installed if the <package>mythes</package> thesaurus is also installed on the system.
      </para>
      <para>
        If <package>mythes</package> is subsequently installed on that system, the <package>mythes-fr</package> package will also automatically be installed due to the weak dependency from the already installed <package>langpacks-fr</package> package.
      </para>
    </important>

    <note role="References">
      <para>
        <code>locale</code>(7), <code>localectl</code>(1), <code>locale.conf</code>(5), <code>vconsole.conf</code>(5), <code>unicode</code>(7), and <code>utf-8</code>(7) man pages
      </para>
      <para>
        Conversions between the names of the graphical desktop environment's X11 layouts and their names in <code>localectl</code> can be found in the file <code>/usr/share/X11/xkb/rules/base.lst</code>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <!-- bending the tagging rules slightly so this table is always all on one
    page for ILT and is also included with the i18n content -->

  <section>
    <title>Language Codes Reference</title>

    <note>
      <para>
        This table might not reflect all langpacks available on your system.
        Use <code>yum info langpacks-<replaceable>SUFFIX</replaceable></code> to get more information about any particular langpacks package.
      </para>
    </note>

    <table frame="all">
      <title>Language Codes</title>
      <tgroup cols="3" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.0*"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="3" colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Language
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Langpacks Suffix
            </entry>
            <entry>
              $LANG value
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              English (US)
            </entry>
            <entry>
              en
            </entry>
            <entry>
              en_US.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Assamese
            </entry>
            <entry>
              as
            </entry>
            <entry>
              as_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Bengali
            </entry>
            <entry>
              bn
            </entry>
            <entry>
              bn_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Chinese (Simplified)
            </entry>
            <entry>
              zh_CN
            </entry>
            <entry>
              zh_CN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Chinese (Traditional)
            </entry>
            <entry>
              zh_TW
            </entry>
            <entry>
              zh_TW.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              French
            </entry>
            <entry>
              fr
            </entry>
            <entry>
              fr_FR.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              German
            </entry>
            <entry>
              de
            </entry>
            <entry>
              de_DE.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Gujarati
            </entry>
            <entry>
              gu
            </entry>
            <entry>
              gu_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Hindi
            </entry>
            <entry>
              hi
            </entry>
            <entry>
              hi_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Italian
            </entry>
            <entry>
              it
            </entry>
            <entry>
              it_IT.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Japanese
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ja
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ja_JP.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Kannada
            </entry>
            <entry>
              kn
            </entry>
            <entry>
              kn_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Korean
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ko
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ko_KR.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Malayalam
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ml
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ml_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Marathi
            </entry>
            <entry>
              mr
            </entry>
            <entry>
              mr_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Odia
            </entry>
            <entry>
              or
            </entry>
            <entry>
              or_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Portuguese (Brazilian)
            </entry>
            <entry>
              pt_BR
            </entry>
            <entry>
              pt_BR.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Punjabi
            </entry>
            <entry>
              pa
            </entry>
            <entry>
              pa_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Russian
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ru
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ru_RU.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Spanish
            </entry>
            <entry>
              es
            </entry>
            <entry>
              es_ES.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Tamil
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ta
            </entry>
            <entry>
              ta_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Telugu
            </entry>
            <entry>
              te
            </entry>
            <entry>
              te_IN.utf8
            </entry>
          </row>
          <!--
            <row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c3"><emphasis>Technology Previews</emphasis></entry></row>
            <row><entry>Maithili</entry><entry>mai_IN.utf8</entry><entry>maithili-support</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Nepali</entry><entry>ne_NP.utf8</entry><entry>nepali-support</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Sinhala</entry><entry>si_LK.utf8</entry><entry>sinhala-support</entry></row> -->
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
</section>
